American Philosophical Society Archives 1743-1984 APS.Archives
American Philosophical Society
- Communications, 1748-1837; III; 4.0 ln. ft.
  - Manuscript communications, 1748-1837; III.1; 3.5 ln. ft.
    - Meteorological Observations made at Washington (3), 1823 April 18- 1824 April 18; 1.0 item; Wallenstein, Jules de (Box 6)
    - Meteorological Observations made at Washington (4), 1823 April 18- 1824 April 18; 1.0 item; Wallenstein, Jules de (Box 6)
    - Meteorological Observations made at Washington (5), 1823 April 18- 1824 April 18; 1.0 item; Wallenstein, Jules de (Box 6)
    - Concerning and improved manner of gauging, 1792 Nov. 16; 1.0 item; W. (Box 6)
    - Concerning the longitude of Philosophical Hall (with report by American Philosophical Society Publications Committee, 1834 August 6), 1833 Oct. 18; 1.0 item; Walker, Sears Cook (Box 6)
    - Concerning phases of the occultation of Jupiter by the moon, 1834 June 27; 1.0 item; Walker, Sears Cook (Box 6)
    - ALS to John Vaughan, 1838 Aug. 15; 1.0 item; Walker, Sears Cook (Box 6)
    - ALS to Richard Peters, 1824 July 2; 1.0 item; Waln, Robert (Box 6)
    - ALS to John C. Calhoun, 1819 Mar. 30; 1.0 item; Walsh, Robert (Box 6)
    - ALS to Peter S. Duponceau, 1827 Dec. 20; 1.0 item; Warden, David Baillie (Box 6)
    - Concerning a meteoric stone which fell at Weston in North American Dec. 4, 1807, 1810 June 15; 1.0 item; Warden, David Baillie (Box OS)
    - ALS to John Adams, 1798 Sept. 25; 1.0 item; Washington, George (Box 6)
    - ALS to Thomas Coombe, Sr., 1772 Feb. 2; 1.0 item; White, Taylor (Box 6)
    - Concerning a possible discovery of an effectual prevention against phthisis pulmonalis, n.d.; 1.0 item; Whitehead, John C. (Box 6)
    - Thermometrical tables taken at Detroit, 1798 Oct. 16-1799 June 17; 1.0 item; Wilkinson, James (Box 6)
    - Meteorological observations taken on a voyage from Detroit ALS to Michilimackinac, 1798 Aug. 4- Sept. 3; 1.0 item; Wilkinson, James (Box 6)
    - Observations of the solar eclipse of Oct. 27, 1780, 1780 Nov. 20; 2.0 items; Willard, Joseph (Box 6)
      Note: contains diagram of the "appearance of spots on the Sun".
    - ALS to Robert Patterson, 1791 Feb. 7; 1.0 item; Williams, Jonathan Jr. (Box 6)
    - ALS to Caspar Wistar, 1800 June 26; 1.0 item; Williams, Jonathan Jr. (Box 6)
    - ALS to Robert Patterson, 1800 May 24; 1.0 item; Williams, Jonathan Jr. (Box 6)
    - ALS to John Vaughan, 1800 Dec. 16; 1.0 item; Williams, Jonathan Jr. (Box 6)
    - ALS to John Vaughan, 1801 April 28; 1.0 item; Williams, Jonathan Jr. (Box 6)
    - Remarks relating ALS to the seasons, 1813 Oct. 15; 1.0 item; Williams, Jonathan Jr. (Box 6)
    - ALS to John Vaughan, 1801 April 6; 1.0 item; Williams, Jonathan Jr. (Box 6)
    - ALS to the American Philosophical Society, 1809 Jan. 8; 1.0 item; Williams, Robert (Box 6)
    - ALS to the American Philosophical Society, 1811 Jan. 24; 1.0 item; Williams, Robert (Box 6)
    - Concerning geological formations, ca.1809 Jan. 8; 1.0 item; Williams, Robert (Box 6)
    - ALS to John Vaughan, 1800 Dec. 8; 2.0 items; Williams, William (Box OS)
    - ALS to Thomas Jefferson, 1797 May 28; 1.0 item; Williamson, Hugh (Box 6)
    - ALS to Thomas Jefferson, 1797 May 24; 1.0 item; Williamson, Hugh (Box 6)
    - Concerning the fascination of serpents, 1804 June 15; 1.0 item; Williamson, Hugh (Box 6)
    - Concerning the parhelia rainbows and halo which appeared in Philadelphia Dec. 21, 1756 [presented by George Logan], 1816 May 20; 1.0 item; Williamson, Hugh (Box 6)
    - ALS to John Vaughan (with two copies), 1805 Dec. 12; 1.0 item; Wilson, Bird (Box 6)
    - Concerning a spinning machine, 1810; 4.0 items; Winpenny and Long (Box 6)
      Note: contains 2 diagrams of "spinning machines".
    - ALS to John Vaughan, n.d.; 1.0 item; Wistar, Caspar (Box 6)
    - Concerning bathing in Sweden, 1772 June 19; 1.0 item; Wrangel, Charles Magnus (Box 6)
    - ALS to John Vaughan, 1832 Dec. 6; 1.0 item; Wuheilhausen, Frederick Jacob (Box 6)
    - ALS to Robert Patterson, 1799 Feb. 27; 1.0 item; Wynkoop, Henry (Box 6)
    - Concerning the prevention of decay in peach trees, 1797 Dec. 26; 1.0 item; X (pseud) (Box 6)
  - Verbal communications, 1801-1807; III.2; 1.0 Vol. (34 pp.)
    Notes of observations, discoveries, publications, and other facts communicated to the Society by members. Among them are reports by Robert Patterson, Benjamin H. Latrobe (on bilious and noxious gas in wells), Caspar Wistar, John Wister (on tree growth), Thomas Gilpin (on placing rafters), Johnathan Williams, and Benjamin S. Barton; also extracts from letters to Barton from Sir Joseph Banks, Peter Curtis, and Richard P. Barton; and extracts from letters from James Winthrop to Francis Nichols, from Thomas Cooper to John Vaughan, and from John Clifford to Caspar Wistar; and also James Wright's description of the Mastodon, copied from Philadelphia Medical and Physical Journal 1, (1804): p. 154.
- Members, 1743-1973; IV; 15.25 ln. ft.
  This record group consists of 13 sub-groups which documents the membership of the Society. It contains such items as letters of nomination (IV.2), letters acknowledging election (IV.3), membership rolls (IV.6), membership certificates (IV.11), and a photograph album (IV.12).
  - Membership and Attendance lists, 1792-1932; IV.1; 6.0 vols. and 1 box
    Contains the following lists: Lists of members, 1792, 1846, 1874, and undated, 4 vols.; List of surviving members, 1885, 1 vol.; List of resident members, 1842-1886, with record of attendance and payment of dues, 4 vols.; Roll of members present at meetings, 1845-1850, 1929-1942, 7 notebooks, 1 ledger.
  - Nominations for membership, 1773-1931; IV.2; 5.5 ln. ft.
    Arranged alphabetically, principally covering the period after 1815, but with a cap fro the 1891-1898 years. Nominations of persons not subsequently elected are, by Society rule, destroyed (an exception is listed below). By the middle of the nineteenth century, nominations were usually conventionally phrased; after 1888 printed forms were often used. See also the minutes of the Committee on Nominations, 1914-1940 (VIII,29).
  - Letters acknowledging election, 1840-1930; IV.3; 5.0 ln. ft.
    Mostly formal letters of acceptance, addressed to the secretary, arranged alphabetically. At one time they were arranged chronologically in six volumes.
  - Membership and elections, 1897-; IV.4; 2.5 ln. ft.
    Includes printed forms used to notify the membership of nominees; lists of those elected, etc. (New members are listed each year in the Year Book).
  - Annual elections, ca. 1771-1931; IV.5; 1.0 box
    Ballots, tabulations, certificates of outside judges authenticating the election of members to the Society.
  - Rolls of members, 1743-1898; IV.6; 2.0 vols.
    One volume, containing the Act of Incorporation and obligations of 1780 on extra pages bound into a copy of APS Transactions, o.s., 1 (1771), has signatures of hundreds of members form Thomas Bond to Emlin Hutchinson in 1898; these pages were reprinted in facsimile in a volume without title, 1896. The second volume, entitled "Laws and Rules of Order of the American Philosophical Society ... followed by a Complete List of Members," prepared by William Fite, and expert calligrapher, 1837, contains similar material and also the name and style of every elected member. After 1837 members (including some elected before that date) signed this roll upon being admitted into the Society. This volume was closed in 1897, when it was superseded by a similar volume, which is still in use. Some members signed both books.
  - Records of deceased members, 1837; IV.7; 1.0 vols. (20 pp.)
    Alphabetical list of members whose dates of death have been ascertained. See the printed lists in Laws and Regulations (1860), p. 25. The record is in John Vaughan's hand.
  - Memoirs of deceased members, 1783-1855; IV.8; 1.0 box
    Some of the memoirs, or obituaries, listed below were published in Society publications. Prior to 1838 memoirs or obituaries, when published, were done so on an ad hoc basis. After that date and until 1937 they appeared in the Prodeedings, and since 1937 they have been printed in the Year Book. The volume contains the following memoirs:
    Frederick Beasley, by George Bacon Wood
    Clement C. Biddle, by George Ord
    Mathew Carey, by Isaac Lea
    Redmond Conyngham, by Alonzo Potter
    William H. Dillingham, by Charles B. Trego
    Louis Stephen Duhail, by M. Davezac
    William Gaston, by William H. Dillingham
    John Gummere, by Robert M. Patterson
    Justus Heinrich Christian Helmuth, by his son
    Joseph Hopkinson, by John Kintzing Kane
    Isaac Rand Jackson, by John Kintzing Kane
    William Stephen Jacobs, by William E. Horner
    Severin Lorich, by F. S. Lorich, with a note by Condy Raguet
    William McIlvaine, by George Ord
    Christian Mayer, by J. M. Buthe
    Joseph Nicholas Nicollet, by John J. Abert
    William Peter, by Job R. Tyson
    Philip Syng Physick, by William E. Horner
    Joseph Priestley, by Joseph Priestly Jr.
    Christian Rask, by George B. Depping
    Henry Reed, by John F. Frazer
    Benjamin Wood Richards, by John Kintzing Kane
    John Sanderson, by John Seely Hart
    Francisco Borja Caracao Stockler, by José Maria Dantas Pereira
    William Strickland by John Kintzing Kane
    Lardner Vanuxem, by Isaac Lea
    Daniel Webster, by Henry A. Boardman
    John Price Wetherill, by John Kintzing Kane
    William White, by William Heathcote DeLancey
    Caspar Wistar, by José Francesco Corrêa da Serra
  - Autographs of members, ca. 1876-1880; IV.9; 1.0 vol. (ca. 65 pp.)
    This scrapbook contains signatures of members, alphabetically arranged, clipped from return postal cards and acknowledgments of the receipt of the Society's publications.
  - Members book, 1808-1896; IV.10; 1.0 vol. (ca. 702 pp.)
    This was compiled between the 1840's and 1896, but is includes names of members prior to that date, as well as their date of election, death (a few obituaries are attached), and there are citations of mentions of the individual in the Proceedings.
  - Membership certificates, 1786-; IV.11; ca. 60 items
    In 1786 the Society for the first time provided members with formal, engraved certificates of election. This is a collection of such certificates, issued to about 60 different members, signed by Benjamin Franklin and other presidents and officers from 1786 to the present time.
  - Photograph Albums, ca. 1880-1900; IV.12; 5.0 vols.
    These photographs of members, collected in the late nineteenth century, include some photographs of paintings. A few are autographed. The images are in no order, but each volume is indexed. There is a separate collection of loose photographs of members which is added to on a more consistent basis presently.
  - Biographical Register, ca. 1800-1973; IV.13; 2.5 ln. ft.
    This register was compiled by Dr. Marion Elderton during the period 1964-1968 and 1970-1974. It includes members elected since 1800 and deceased as of 1968, with a few entries to 1973.
- Officers, 1769-1978; V; 43.0 ln. ft.
  Contains records for various officers of the Society (president, secretary, executive officer, treasurer, and officers and council). This record group does not contain the records for all the Society's presidents and officers. However, it does provide an account of the operation of the Society to the early twentieth century.
  - President, 1853-1938; V.1; 3.0 ln. ft., 3 vols.
    - Presidential Addresses, 1853 and 1854; V.1.a; 1.0 vol.; Bache, Franklin (President 1853-1855)
      The address of 1853 is principally on scientific associations; that of 1854 is on APS business. Brief resumes are printed in APS Proceedings 5 (1848-1853): 360, and 6 (1854-1858): 67.
    - Presidential Addresses, 1860; V.1.b; 1.0 vol.; Wood, George Bacon (President 1859-1879)
      He discusses hasty generalizations in science, and also Society business. Printed in APS Proceedings 7 (1859-1861): 331.
    - Presidential reports, 1908-1909, 1911-1916; V.1.c; 2.0 folders; Keen, William W., (William Williams), b. 1837
      Manuscripts of reports read at the annual meetings of the APS. These do not appear in the printed minutes in APS Proceedings of the period.
    - Correspondence, 1921-1925; V.1.d; 1.0 folder; Scott, William B. (President, 1918-1925)
    - Correspondence, 1927-1931; V.1.e; 2.5 ln. ft.; Dercum, Francis X. (President, 1927-1931)
    - Correspondence, 1932-1938; V.1.f; 0.5 ln. ft.; Morris, Roland Sletor (President, 1932-1942)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1913-1921; V.1.g; 1.0 folder; Conklin, Edwin Grant, 1863-1952
      Correspondence and other data relating to his participation in APS affairs, but prior to his term as President. It is mainly routine correspondence, including notices of committee appointments and meetings, etc. For his term as Executive Officer of the APS (1936-1942) see his correspondence under Archives V,c.
  - Secretary, 1789-1939; V.2; 34.0 ln. ft., 3 vols.
    - Journal of the proceedings, 1789-1823, 1837-1852; V.2.a; 3.0 vols.
      Drafts and copies of outgoing letters, principally to newly elected members and to booksellers and agents, mostly in the hand of John Vaughan (to 1841) and Charles B. Trego. Typed index (18 pages).
      Copies and record of outgoing correspondence, February 17, 1837 - 0ctober 13, 1843, 183 pages. List showing distribution of Proceedings and Transactions; periodicals needed by library pages 184-291, October 17, 1843 - February 8, 1852, 122 pages.
    - Correspondence, 1887-1888, 1891-1921; V.2.b; 5.5 ln. ft.
      Press and carbon copies of outgoing letters, mostly of a routine character, but giving a very clear picture of behind-the-scenes activities at the Society.
    - Correspondence, 1909-1939; V.2.c; 28.5 ln. ft.
      A miscellaneous collection of incoming correspondence, primarily on routine Society business. Because many committee members lived away from Philadelphia, as well as some of the Presidents and Officers, the series includes correspondence with these individuals as well. All types of Society business are to be found discussed in the correspondence.
  - Executive Office, 1940-1941; V.3; 3.5 ln. ft.
    - Correspondence, 1940-1941; V.3.a; 3.5 ln. ft.; Conklin, Edwin Grant, 1863-1952
  - Treasurer, 1772-1936; V.4; 9.5 ln. ft., 41 vols.
    - Accounts, 1782-1920; V.4.a; 11.0 vols.
      Later called Cash Books. In the first volume are memoranda on leases of space to the College of Physicians, the Philadelphia Society for Promoting Agriculture, the Pennsylvania Horticultural Society, Athenaeum of Philadelphia, Historical Society of Pennsylvania, Kappa Lambda fraternity, Charles Willson Peale, and Thomas Sully; accounts with Robert Aitken and George Turner; subscriptions for the portrait of Joseph Priestley; accounts of the Observatory Fund and the Magellanic Fund.
    - Accounts, 1772-1899; V.4.b; 19.0 items
      A miscellaneous group of accounts includes records (1785-1792) relating to the construction of Philosophical Hall; repairs to the Hall (1816-1820); receipts of Benjamin Franklin's bond (1791-1792); a receipt signed by Franklin; a few accounts of the Pennsylvania Silk Society (ca. 1770-1784); and a few other items. These records were discovered in the Philosophical Hall vault in 1979 (for an account of this see: Committee on Library Report, 197. Year Book pp. 158-160). A few other items were not strictly Treasurer's accounts (e.g. André Michaux's subscription list for exploring the American West, 1793) and they are catalogued separately. table of contents (1 p.).
    - Ledgers, 1844-1919; V.4.c; 6.0 vols.
    - Miscellaneous financial records, 1779-1937; V.4.d; 4.5 ln. ft.
      Treasurer's yearly accounts (ca. 1779-1930); bank books (1798-1863), check books (1836-1920), canceled checks (1837-1920), bills and receipts (1834-1937)
    - Financial Statements and Reports, 1914-1936; V.4.e; 0.5 ln. ft.
      Printed
    - Subscription books, 1817-1826, 1838; V.4.f; 11.0 vols
      Three volumes, 1817-1826, kept by John Vaughan, contain records of subscriptions for (1) the purchase of Gotthilf H. Muhlenberg's herbarium, 1817, and for the works of Buffon in 127 vols., 1817-1818; (2) for the second volume of the Transactions of the historical and Literary Committee and for the Philadelphia Chamber of Commerce, 1825; and (3) for the Chamber of Commerce (the latter apparently one of Vaughan's other interests). Two volumes contain subscriptions for the publication of Transactions, n.s., 3 (1826); and on of the publication of DuPonceau's treatise on the Chinese language, 1838.
      In addition, there are invoices, receipts, records of members' annual contributions, lists of securities, and "Contingent Expenses and Post Office" which records expenditures for printing and postal expenses; and minutes of the auditing committee, 1922-1937 (1 vol.)
  - Officers and Council, 1804-1926; V.5; 2.0 vols.
    - Minutes, 1804-1926; V.5.a; 2.0 vols.
      The officers and council acted as a kind of executive committee of the Society, under the by-laws of 1804.
- Curators, 1769-1978; VI; 2.75 ln. ft.
  Documents donations to the Society's cabinet of curiosity, as well as other artifacts.
  - Curator's records, 1793-1978; VI.1; 2.0 ln. ft.
    Includes items in individual folders that have been separately catalogued in the library; reports of curators, 1876-1938 (1 box); correspondence, lists of items, etc., 1818-1943, 1978. There are also records, 1957-1965 (2 boxes), kept by Henri Marceau (Curator, 1957-1969); and one unsorted box of miscellaneous items (ca. 1780's-1890's)
  - Donation book, 1818-1831; VI.2; 1.0 vol.
    Rough notes by John Vaughan, with miscellaneous letters, concerning gifts to the cabinet of APS.
  - Donation to the cabinet, 1834-1899; VI.3; 1.0 vol.
    A continuation of the Donation book; a record of gifts of fossils, minerals, coins, medals, etc., by Thomas Jefferson, Joseph Sansom, William Short, Joel R. Poinsett, William H. Keating, and others.
  - Curator's record books, 1769-1900; VI.4; 6.0 vols.
    Gifts to the cabinet and all actions of the Society respecting its collections, abstracted from the minutes. Two of the volumes are indexes to donors and gifts. Presented by Curators, 1899.
  - Portraits and busts in the collections of the American Philosophical Society, 1898; VI.5; 1.0 vol.; Sachse, Julius F. (1842-1919)
    69 prints from negatives made by Sachse, most of them superior to the photographs reproduced in Catalogue of Portraits ... in the ... American Philosophical Society(APS Memoirs 54), which otherwise supersedes it.
  - Preliminary notes for Curator's catalogue of portraits, busts, and bas-reliefs in the collection of the American Philosophical Society, 1898-1901; VI.5; 1.0 vol.; Petit, Henry (1842-1921)
    Biographical sketches and memoranda.
- Library, 1798-1977; VII; 48.75 ln. ft.
  Consists of 14 sub-groups which document through correspondence, minutes, reports, record books and catalogues the development and routine business of the Society's Library and its collections. Additionally, there are records which relate to the building of Library Hall in the late 1950s.
  - Librarian, 1862-1977; VII.1; 81.5 ln. ft., 1 box
    - Annual and Special Reports, 1862-1936; VII.1.a; 1.0 box
    - Correspondence, 1900-1977; VII.1.b; 81.5 ln. ft.
      A large, diverse, and comprehensive series of correspondence, reports, lists, and miscellaneous materials collected during the tenures of five Librarians (to date): Isaac Minis Hays (1897-1922), Laura E. Hanson (1926-1941), William E. Lingelbach (1942-1958), Richard H. Shryock (1958-1965), and Whitfield J. Bell, Jr. (1966-1980). The correspondence prior to about 1940 tends to be more routine in nature. As the focus of the Library and its collections was better defined after 1940, an under the dynamic leadership of Lingelbach, Shryock, and Bell, the data produced and saved was more diverse, reflecting on all aspects of the Library's development, both internal, and external sponsorship in the wider library community (e.g. there is correspondence with Library research associates; records concerning local and national meetings, conferences and symposia participated in or sponsored by the Library; Library committee records, 1942-1976, pulled from the Librarian's correspondence files, which includes notes and other background data not found in the Library Committee Minutes).
      The scholarly interests of each of these later Librarians - Lingelbach (American history, Benjamin Franklin, European diplomatic history, historic conservation), Shryock (history of medicine and science), Bell (history of medicine, early American history, history of science) - is reflected in their Librarian's papers, since they participated as Librarians, on numerous committees and organizations which interested them, not all of which pertained strictly to APS Library business. There is, for example, much on the development of Independence National Historical Park, and the larger interest of conservation in Pennsylvania and nation-wide, in Lingelbach's files.
  - Collections, 1798-1954; VII.2; 59.0 vols., 24.5 ln. ft.
    - Accession records, n.d.; VII.2.a; 16.0 vols.
    - Bills of parcels of books, 1815-1832; VII.2.b; 2.0 vols.
      Records and receipts of books from booksellers and at auction, including purchases from the libraries of Benjamin Smith Barton, Nicholas Collin, Alexander J. Dallas, and Joseph Priestly.
    - Donation books, 1899-1954; VII.2.c; 11.0 vols. & 1 index vol.
      Record of gifts to Library and Cabinet, including books, portraits, busts, medals, artifacts, specimens of natural history, and mechanical models.
    - Library withdrawals, 1915-1949; VII.2.d; 1.0 vol.
      Record of books, mostly periodicals, withdrawn from the catalogue, principally for sale or gift to other institutions. The most unusual item is the Tribute Roll of Montezuma, presented to the National Museum of Mexico, 1942.
    - Loan books, 1803-1941; VII.2.e; 3.0 vols.
      Record of borrowings from the Library of members and others. The first and third volumes, 1803-1835 and 1889-1941, are in the form of printed promissory notes to return the volume or forfeit a sum of money (the financial forfeiture was disregarded after about 1900). The first volume is indexed by borrower. This volume also contains a copy of the library regulations drawn from the minutes and by-laws, 1802-1816, and several pages headed "Account of Importation of Journals by the Treasurer," 1803-1831.
    - Library book, 1873-1883, 1885-1888; VII.2.f; 1.0 vol.
      Record of letters, accessions, borrowings, and other library business.
    - Catalogues, 1798-1884; VII.2.g; 10.0 vols.
      The following manuscript catalogues of the Library are preserved:
      - Catalogue of the Library, 1798; 2.0 vols.
        Apparently prepared with a view to publication.
      - Catalogue of the Library, 1799; 2.0 vols.; Nicholas Collin
      - Catalogue of the Library, 1814; 1.0 vols.
        The titles are arranged alphabetically by author, with case and shelf number of the volume, and the name of the donor. Notation explains: "This Book was delivered by the Stationer on Tuesday 18th of January 1814 - the Catalogue was finished on Friday the 25th of February 1814, i.e., a Space of 33 days (Sundays excepted.)"
      - Catalogue of the Library, 1836; 1.0 vols.
        Begun by John Vaughan, one volume is rough, the other volume is fair..
      - Catalogue of manuscripts register, ca. 1840; 1.0 vol.
        An alphabetical list of authors, translators, editors, etc.
      - Index to catalogue of the Library, Vol. 2. List of authors, translators, &c, ca. 1840; 1.0 vol.
      - Author index to Catalogue of the American Philosophical Society Library, 1863-1884; 1.0 vol.
    - Collections Files (legal file), VII.2.h; 24.0 ln. ft.